Welcome to Africa! Or rather, I should say, welcome home.
مرحباً بكم في أفريقيا! أو يمكنني القول مرحباً بكم في منزلكم.
Because this is where it all really began, isn't it?
ﻷن هذا هو المكان الذي بدأنا منه جميعاً، أليس كذلك؟
Looking at fossils dating back several millions of years --
بالنظر إلى حفريات عدة تعود إلى عدة ملايين من السنين --
it all points to evidence that life
كل ذلك يشير إلى أدلة أن الحياة
for the human species as we know it began right here.
للأنواع البشرية كما نعلم بدأت هنا.
We are on an amazing journey the next four days.
نحن في رحلة مذهلة في الأربعة أيام القادمة.
You're going to hear stories of "Africa: The Next Chapter."
سنستمع إلى قصص من أفريقيا: الفصل الثاني.
Fantastic tales, anecdotes from speakers.
حكايات رائعة، ونادرة من المتكلمين.
But I want to turn that upside down for a moment,
ولكني أريد أن أقلب ذلك رأساً على عقب لبرهة.
and get something out on the table and clear the air so to say.
ونحصل على شئ على الطاولة وننظف الهواء، إذاً لنقول.
What's the worst thing you've ever heard about Africa?
ما هو أسوأ شئ إطلاقاً سمعتموه عن أفريقيا؟
And this is not a rhetorical question.
وهذا ليس سؤال بلاغة .
I actually want answers from you.
أنا حقيقة أريد إجابات منكم.
Go for it! The worst.
قولوها! الأسوأ.
Famine.
المجاعة.
Corruption.
الفساد.
More.
المزيد.
Genocide.
الإبادة الجماعية.
AIDS.
الأيدز.
Slavery.
العبودية والرق.
That's enough.
هذا يكفي.
We've all heard these things.
كلنا سمعنا هذه الأشياء.
But this is about Africa, the story we have not heard.
ولكن هذه عن أفريقيا، القصة التي لم نسمعها بعد.
The stories that we want to know,
القصص التي يجب أن نعرفها ،
and the stories that do exist about positive tales.
القصص الموجودة عن الحكايات الإيجابية.
A part of my talk is going to be about investment opportunities
جزء من كلامي سيكون حول الفرص الإستثمارية
that exist on this continent,
الموجودة في هذه القارة.
to separate the rhetoric from the reality, the fact from the fiction.
لفصل الخطاب من الواقع، والحقيقة من الخيال.
To go to the actual data and statistics that exist
للذهاب للبيانات الحقيقية والإحصاءات الموجودة
about the actual things that are happening on the ground
عن الأشياء الحقيقية التي تحصل على الأرض
that make Africa a realistic investment opportunity and option for you.
التي تجعل أفريقيا فرصة إستثمار حقيقية وخيار لكم.
So let's get going because Africa,
لذلك دعونا نمضي لأن أفريقيا،
to some degree, is on a turnaround.
إلى حد ما، تمضي نحو التحول.
A turnaround in terms of how it manages its image,
تحول من حيث الكيفية التي تنظم بها صورتها،
and how it takes control of its own destiny.
وكيف تتحكم في مصيرها.
And turnarounds are part and parcel
والتحولات هي جزء لا يتجزأ
of what I have focused on for most of my professional career.
في ما كنت قد ركزت عليه في معظم حياتي المهنية.
And it all started almost a decade ago,
وبدأ كل شئ منذ عقد تقريباً،
as a young consultant at McKinsey &amp; Company
كمستشار شاب في شركة ماكينزي
at their first African office in Johannesburg.
في مكتبهم الأفريقي الأول في جوهانسبرج.
And there we worked with leading CEOs
وهنالك عملنا مع كبار المديرين التنفيذين الرواد
on African issues, and African companies on turnarounds,
على المشاكل الأفريقية، والشركات الأفريقية التي تتحول --
making the companies not just the best in Africa
جاعلةً الشركات ليست فقط الأفضل في أفريقيا،
but the best globally.
لكن الأفضل عالمياً.
But I really formalized this focus on turnarounds
لكني جعلت تركيزي حقاً على التحولات
when I was completing my MBA in the United States.
عندما أكملت ماجستير إدارة الأعمال في الولايات المتحدة.
It all began with a fantastic phone call.
كل ذلك بدأ بمكالمة رائعة.
It was from Rosabeth Moss Kanter,
كانت من روسبيتث موس كانتر،
Harvard Business School guru and a professor of mine.
رئيسة مدرسة أعمال هارفارد وأستاذي.
And she said, "I want to write a case, Euvin --
وقالت، " أريد أن أكتب قضية، يا إيوفن --
a case on a public-sector leader
قضية عن قائد في القطاع العام
that has lessons for the corporate world."
يكون لديه دروس لعالم الشركات."
And the leader that came to mind was Nelson Mandela.
والقائد الذي فكرت فيه هو نيلسون مانديلا.
Because Nelson Mandela, as he took over power
ﻷن نيلسون مانديلا، عقب توليه السلطة
as the first democratically-elected president of South Africa,
كأول رئيس ديمقراطي منتخب في جنوب أفريقيا،
faced a situation of a country
واجه وضع الدولة
that could have slid into the abyss of chaos.
الذي يمكن أن ينزلق به إلى هاوية الفوضى.
But he started the country on a path of a positive cycle.
ولكن بدأ الدولة في مسار دائري إيجابي,
Now the case, "Nelson Mandela: Change Leader,"
الآن القضية، "نيلسون مانيلا: قائد التغيير،"
became part of the research base for a chapter
أصبحت جزءاً من قاعدة البحوث للفصل
in Rosabeth's new book called "Confidence."
في كتاب روسبيث الجديد، يُدعى "الثقة".
And "Confidence" became a New York Times bestseller
و"الثقة" أصبح أفضل مبيعات نيويورك تايمز
and topped Business Week's hardcover bestseller list.
وتصدرت الغلاف الفني لبيزنس ويك في قائمة أكثر الكتب مبيعا.
And why I tell you this story is because later, when I was interviewed
ولماذا سأحكي لكم هذه القصة ﻷن سابقاً، عندما تم إستضافتي
on SABC Africa, on a pan-African broadcast, they asked,
على سابك أفريكا، على إذاعة بان أفريكا، سألوني،،
"What is your key lesson, or the key thing you enjoy the most?" --
"ما هو الدرس الرئيسي، أو الشئ الرئيسي الذي أستمتعت به أكثر؟" --
because it was a huge privilege to be part of such a project.
لأنه لشرف كبير أن أكون جزءا من هذا المشروع.
The lesson from that was that it was Africa -- an African story --
والدرس من ذلك أنه أن أفريقيا، قصة أفريقية،
that was used to share news with the rest of the world
تستخدم لمشاركة الأخبار مع بقية العالم
of what the benchmark can be for corporate turnarounds.
ما يمكن أن يكون معياراً لتحول الشراكة.
Africa was being used as a success story!
أفريقيا كانت تستخدم بوصفها قصة ناجحة!
So I want to share with you a personal story
لذلك أريد أن أشارككم قصة شخصية
about a turnaround or a transformation.
حول التحول أو التحويل.
And that has to do with me
والذي له علاقة بي.
because in 1994, I packed a few things into a backpack
ﻷنه في 1994، حزمت بعض الأشياء في حقيبة الظهر
and headed off for a year of travel
وأتجهت لمدة سنة من السفر
in the middle of my university career.
أثناء مسيرتي الجامعية.
You should have seen my parents' reaction!
كان عليكم أن تروا ردة فعل والداي!
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But very soon, I found myself from the southern part of Africa,
ولكن بسرعة جداً، وجدت نفسي من الجزء الجنوبي لأفريقيا --
in South Africa -- at the very north, in Egypt.
في شمال أفريقيا، في أقصى الشمال، في مصر.
And I sought out the most remote places.
ورأيت أماكن بعيدة جداً.
I went to the Siwa Oasis. That was one of my stops.
ذهبت إلى واحة سيوا -- التي كانت واحدة من أماكن توقفي.
And the Siwa Oasis is famous for several things,
وواحة سيوا مشهورة بعدة أشياء،
but the key thing is that it was the place
لكن الشئ الرئيسي هو أنه كان المكان
that Alexander the Great went to
الذي ذهب إليه إلكساندر الأعظم
when he wanted to find out what his destiny had in store for him.
عندما أراد معرفة مصيره الذي كان ينتظره.
And legend has it that Alexander trekked through this desert.
وتقول الأسطورة أن إلكساندر عبر هذه الصحراء.
Half his battalion was wiped out in the sandstorm.
نصف كتيبته كانت تتنزه في عاصفة رملية.
And myth says that he had an audience with the oracle,
وتقول الاسطورة انه اجرى مقابلة مع أوراكل ،
and it foretold his destiny of greatness.
وتنبأ له بمصيره العظيم.
This was 300 BC.
هذا كان 300 سنة قبل الميلاد.
So Africa had long been seen as a place to go to for answers.
إذاً أفريقيا من زمن ينظر عليها على أنها مكان تذهب له للبحث عن إجابة.
Now, the thing I remember about Siwa
الآن، الشئ الذي أتذكره عن سيوا
was the magical view of the sky at night.
المنظر السحري للسماء في الليل.
With no natural light source, Siva is one of these amazing places
مع عدم وجود مصدر الضوء الطبيعي ، سيوا هي أحد هذه الأماكن المدهشة
that when you look up you see a perfect tapestry.
عندما تنظر تجد نسيج متكامل.
Fast forward to 2002.
نذهب بسرعة لعام 2002.
I'm sitting in Cambridge, Massachusetts
كنت أجلس في كامبيردج، ماساتشوستس
at the Healthcare Development Conference.
في مؤتمر تطوير الرعاية الصحية.
And I see the same picture, but from the opposite side.
وأنا أرى نفس الصورة، لكن من الجهة الأخرى.
A satellite picture looking down at the earth.
صورة قمر إصطناعي موجه نحو الأرض.
And it was that picture that made such a profound impact on me
وتركت تلك الصورة أثر عميق في نفسي
because I'll never forget it. I remember the very moment.
ﻷني لن أنساها إطلاقاً. أتذكر كل لحظة.
And I wanted to share that image with you of what I saw at that point.
وأردت أن أشارككم تلك الصورة بما رأيته في تلك النقطة.
The first thing that I saw was North America at night --
أول شئ رأيته كان شمال أمريكا في الليل --
glowing, in all its glory. A warm feeling. Light.
متوهجة ، كلها متوهجة. مشاعر دافئة. ضوء.
And then I saw it -- Africa. Quite literally the "Dark Continent."
من ثم رأيت -- أفريقيا. بكل معنى الكلمة "القارة المظلمة".
And while Africa may be dark,
بينما أفريقيا قد تكون مظلمة،
the thing that brought the message home to me
الشئ الذي أرجع لي الرسالة مجدداً
was that this is the challenge we are facing,
كان ذاك هو التحدي الذي نواجهه،
but it's also the opportunity.
لكنها أيضاً الفرصة.
Because whilst Africa may be dark -- other than the few specks
ﻷن أفريقيا بينما هي مظلمة -- بخلاف بقع قليلة
that exist north and in the south and other areas --
موجودة في الشمال وبعض المناطق في الجنوب --
it's aglow with the light in the hearts
إنها متوهجة ومنيرة في قلوب
of the millions of people that are there.
الملايين من الناس هناك.
Entrepreneurs, dynamic people, people with hope.
أصحاب المشاريع، أناس حركيين ، أناس لديهم أمل.
It was George Kimble, the geographer, who said
كان جورج كيمبل، الجغرافي، الذي قال
that, "The only thing dark about Africa is our ignorance of it."
إن ، "الشيء الوحيد المظلم حول افريقيا هو جهلنا بها".
So let's start shedding light on this amazing eclectic continent
لذلك دعونا نبدأ تسليط الضوء على هذه القارة الإنتقائية المذهلة
that has so much to offer.
التي لديها الكثير لتمنحه.
Let's start unpacking it.
دعونا نبدأ بفك تلك الحزم.
Africa is the second-largest continent, a landmass second from Asia.
افريقيا هي ثاني أكبر قارة، من حيث كتلة الأرض، والثانية بعد آسيا.
It also is the second most populated continent,
كما أنها ثاني أكثر القارات إكتظاظاً بالسكان، ،
with 900 million people.
بـ 900 مليون شخص.
In fact -- coming back to the land mass -- Africa is so big
في الحقيقة -- نرجع لكتلة الأرض -- أفريقيا كبيرة جداً
that you could fit in the continental United States,
التي يمكن أن تلائم داخلها قارات الولايات المتحدة ،
China, and the entire Europe into Africa, and still have space.
والصين، وأوروبا بأسرها في أفريقيا، وما تزال هناك مساحة.
Africa is home to over 1,000 languages --
أفريقيا هي مسكن لألف لغة --
2,000 is another estimate that's out there --
و2,000 أخرى مقدرة خارجها --
with over 2,000 languages and dialects.
وفوق الـ 2,000 لغة ولهجة.
But you could say, "Invest in Africa in over 1,000 languages,
لكن يمكنكم القول، "الإستثمار في أفريقيا فوق الـ 1,000 لغة،
and it wouldn't make a difference."
ولن تحدث فرقاً."
What does the data say?
ماذا تقول البيانات؟
As an investment banker, I'm in the cross-flow of information
كمستثمر بنكي، تمر علي المعلومات
and the changes that are taking place in capital markets.
والتغيير الذي يأخذ مكانه في الأسواق الكبرى.
So I want to share with you some of these bellwether signals, or signs,
لذلك أريد أن أشارككم بعض هذه الإشارات الكرازية، أو العلامات،
and winds of change that are sweeping this continent.
ورياح التغيير التي تجتاح هذه القارة.
So let's start on that.
لنبدأ بذلك.
And let's start at the high level, on the macro-factors.
ودعونا نبدأ على مستوى عال، على العوامل الكلية.
Inflation, in general, is coming down across Africa --
التضخم، وبصفة عامة، إنه ينخفض في افريقيا --
that's the first sign --
هذه الإشارة الأولى --
in many countries reaching double-digit figures.
في كثير من البلدان تصل الى ارقام مزدوجة.
So let's start looking at some of those.
لذلك لنبدأ ننظر في بعض منهم.
I call it my Z.E.N. cluster.
أسميها كتلة زت.إي.إن خاصتي.
Zambia: from 2004 to 2006, moves from the 18 percent in inflation
زامبيا: من 2004 إلى 2006 تحرك التضخم من 18 بالمائة
to the nine percent.
إلى تسعة بالمائة
Egypt: from the 16 percent to about 8.4 percent.
مصر: من 16 بالمائة إلى 8.4 بالمائة.
Nigeria: a similar situation,
نيجيريا، وضع مماثل:
from the 16 percent to the eight percent. Single digits.
من 16 بالمائة إلى 8 بالمائة. رقم أحادي.
More fascinating, you have other countries -- South Africa,
أكثر روعة، لديكم دول أخرى -- جنوب أفريقيا،
Mauritius, Namibia -- all in single digits.
موريشيوس، وناميبيا -- كلهم في أرقام أحادية.
But that's just part of the story. You have a similar trend with currencies --
ولكن هذا مجرد جزء من القصة. لديكم اتجاها مماثلا مع العملات --
currencies going through an extreme time of stability.
العملات تمر في الوقت النهائي للإستقرار.
But that's looking at the big picture.
ولكن هذا يبدوا بالنظر للصورة كبيرة.
And the first myth to dispel is that Africa is not a country.
والخرافة الأولى التي يجب تبديدها هي أن أفريقيا ليست دولة.
It's made up --
انها تتكون --
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
It's made up of 53 different countries.
إنها تتكون من 53 دولة مختلفة.
So the very definition -- to say "invest in Africa" is a no-go.
لذا فإن التعريف جداً-- ليقول "الاستثمار فى افريقيا" -- غير مناسب.
It's meaningless.
انه بلا معنى .
Each country has a unique value proposition.
كل بلد له قيمة عرضه الفريدة.
You can make money, you can lose money in Africa.
يمكنك كسب المال، أو يمكنك أن تخسره في أفريقيا.
But opportunities, boy oh boy, they exist.
ولكن الفرص المثيرة موجودة.
And this is what today is about --
وهذا ما نحن بصدده اليوم --
it's about discussing those very opportunities.
لنناقش هذه الفرص.
So let's start getting into the countries
لذلك دعونا نبدأ بالدخول للدول.
and into the specific material and data.
وإلى المواد والبيانات المحددة.
I was recently elected, as Emeka mentioned,
أنا انتخبت مؤخرا، كما ذكرت لايميكا،
as the President of the South African Chamber of Commerce in America.
كرئيس لغرفة التجارة الأفريقية في الولايات المتحدة.
And I'm very proud and happy to be in that role
وأنا فخور وسعيد جداً ﻷكون في هذا الدور
because it is a fascinating position to be in.
ﻷنه وضع قمة في الروعة لتكون هناك.
To hear this dialogue that's just increasing in tenor and velocity,
لسماع هذا الحوار الذي يزيد فحوى وسرعة،
of decisions about trade and companies wanting to come.
لقرارت عن التجارة والشركات التي تريد أن تأتي.
So the first port of call: let's talk a little bit about South Africa.
إذا الجزء الأول من الحديث: دعونا نتحدث قليلاً عن جنوب أفريقيا.
But not the South Africa we always talk about --
لكن ليست جنوب أفريقيا التي نتحدث عنها دوماً --
the gold, the minerals, the First World infrastructure --
الذهب، المعادن، البنية التحتية على المستوى العالمي --
a bit about the other side of it.
قليلاً عن الجانب الآخر منها.
For example, South Africa was recently voted as the top destination
مثال: جنوب أفريقيا تم التصويت لها على أنها أعلى وجهة
for the top 1,000 UK companies for offshore call-centers.
لـ 1,000 من أفضل شركات بريطانيا لتفتتح مراكزاً لها في الخارج.
Same language, timeline, et cetera. Makes sense.
نفس اللغة، الجدول الزمني، ..الخ، يعني الكثير.
Other headlines that have recently reached South Africa
بعض رئاسة الشركات التي وصلت مؤخراً لجنوب أفريقيا
were Bain Capital and KKR, the big boys of private equity.
كانت باين كابيتال و كيه كيه آر ، عمالقة أعمال الأسهم الخاصة.
Headline in South Africa: "They have landed." Quite ominous.
عنوان رئيسي في جنوب أفريقيا: "لقد وصلوا ". أمر ينذر بالسوء.
But what were they there for? To acquire assets.
ولكن لماذا جاءوا إلى هناك؟ للإستحواذ على الأصول.
Bing Capital's acquisition of Edcon, a large retailer, is testimony
إستحواذ بنج كابيتال على إيدكون، متاجر التجزئة الكبيرة، هو شهادة
to the confidence they are starting to place in the economy.
للثقة التي بدأت تحدث في الاقتصاد.
Because it is actually a long-term play.
لأنه هو في الواقع لعب على المدى الطويل.
Being a retailer, it is a play on the belief
أن تصبح متاجر تجزئة، هو لعب على الإيمان
that this middle-class that's growing will continue to grow,
ان هذه الطبقة المتوسطة المتنامية التي سوف تستمر في النمو ،
that the boom and the confidence in consumer spending will continue.
ان الازدهار والثقة في انفاق المستهلكين سوف تستمر.
But the story of Africa, and my focus, is beyond South Africa
ولكن قصة افريقيا، ومحور إهتمامي، هو أبعد من جنوب أفريقيا
because there's so much happening.
ﻷن هنالك كثير من الذي يحصل.
Undoubtedly, Nigeria is clearly a hot spot.
مما لا شك فيه، واضح أن نيجيريا بقعة ساخنة.
Challenges -- and we will hear a lot about Nigeria in these four days.
التحديات -- وسنسمع الكثير عن نيجيريا في الأربعة أيام القادمة.
But looking at Goldman Sachs' work -- we had the famous BRIC Report.
لكن بالنظر إلى عمل غولدمان ساكس -- كان لدينا تقرير بريك الشهير .
The new report, "The Next Eleven," highlights that by 2020
التقرير الجديد، "الأحدى عشر التالية"، يسلط الضوء على أنه بحلول عام 2020
Nigeria is going to be amongst the top 10 economies in the world.
ستصبح نيجيريا من أفضل 10 دول إقتصاداً في العالم.
It's an investment opportunity. Think about that.
وهي فرصة إستثمارية. فكّروا في ذلك.
Is anyone -- our banks, our investors --
إن أي شخص -- بنوكنا، مستثمرينا --
seriously thinking about going to Nigeria?
فكروا بجدية في الذهاب لنيجيريا؟
If you haven't, why not?
إذا لم تكن قد ذهبت ، لم لا؟
What's going on in Nigeria? A couple of things.
ماذا يحدث في نيجيريا؟ عدة أشياء.
I want to talk about it from the perspective of capital markets.
أريد أن أتحدث عنها من منظور أسواق رأس المال.
Bellwether signs again.
علامات الكراز مرة أخرى.
Guarantee Trust Bank recently issued the first Euro Bond
أصدر بنك تراست مؤخرا أول سند باليورو
out of Africa, and this excludes South Africa.
من أفريقيا، ولا يشمل ذلك جنوب أفريقيا.
But the first Eurobond, the raising of international capital
لكن سندات اليورو الأولى، ورفع رأس المال الدولي
offshore, off its own balance sheet,
في الخارج، من ميزانيتها العمومية،
without any sovereign backing --
دون اي دعم سيادي --
that is an indication of the confidence that is taking place in that economy.
هذا هو مؤشر على الثقة التي تجري في هذا الاقتصاد.
Without any sovereign backing,
دون اي دعم سيادي،
a Nigerian company raising capital offshore.
شركة نيجيرية تزيد رأسمالها في الخارج.
It's just a sign of things to come.
انها مجرد دلالة على أشياء مقبلة.
Looking at the oil industry, Africa provides 18 percent
للبحث في صناعة النفط، وأفريقيا توفر 18 في المئة
of the U.S.'s oil supply, with the Middle East just 16 percent.
من نفط الولايات المتحدة، مع الشرق الأوسط 16 في المئة فقط.
It's an important strategic partner.
إنها شريك إستراتيجي مهم.
Let's put Nigeria in perspective.
دعونا نضع في نيجيريا في المنظور.
2.2 to 2.4 million barrels of oil a day --
2.2 الى 2.4 مليون برميل من النفط يوميا.
the same league as Kuwait, the same league as Venezuela.
نفس دور الكويت. نفس دور فنزويلا.
But with Africa, let's start being careful about this.
لكن بالنسبة لأفريقيا، لنكن حذرين حول هذا.
And Emeka and I have had these discussions.
وقد ناقشنا هذا إيميكا وأنا.
We have to move away from what's called "the curse of the commodities."
علينا أن نبتعد عن ما يسمى "لعنة السلع."
Because it's not about oil, it's not about commodities.
ﻷن هذا ليس عن النفط، ليس عن السلع.
For Africa to truly be sustainable,
من أجل أن تصبح أفريقيا مستدامة حقا،
we have to move beyond to other industries.
علينا أن نتجاوزها ، إلى غيرها من الصناعات.
So let's unpack those very quickly,
لذلك دعونا نذكر تلك بشكل سريع جدا ،
and I'm going to move through these very, very, very fast
وسأمر عليها بسرعة كبيرة جدا جدا،
because I can see that clock counting down.
ﻷنني أرى الساعة في العد التنازلي.
What else is going on there? Egypt.
ماذا يجري أيضاً هناك؟ مصر.
Egypt is launching a first large industrial zone --
مصر تطلق أول منطقة صناعية كبيرة --
2.8 billion investment.
2.8 مليار دولار للاستثمار.
The announcement just came out the last few weeks.
الإعلان خرج للتو في الاسابيع القليلة الماضية.
Close to the Mediterranean, near Alexandria --
على مقربة من البحر الأبيض المتوسط، بالقرب من الاسكندرية --
textiles, petrochemicals.
المنسوجات، البتروكيماويات.
It's being managed by a Singaporean-based management company.
وهي تدار من قبل شركة إدارية مقرها سنغافورة.
So they want to emerge as an industrial powerhouse
إذاً انهم يريدون الظهور كقوة صناعية
across the industries -- away from oil.
عبر الصناعات -- بعيدا عن النفط.
Let's look at agriculture. Let's look at forestry.
دعونا ننظر في الزراعة. دعونا ننظر في الغابات.
What's going on there?
ماذا يحصل هناك؟
In Tanzania last week, we had the launch
في تنزانيا الاسبوع الماضي، لدينا إنطلاقة
of the East African Organic Produce Standard.
معيار المنتجات الزراعية العضوية في شرق أفريقيا.
Again, gathering together farmers, gathering together stakeholders
مرة أخرى، جمع المزارعين معاً، وجمع أصحاب المصالح
in East Africa to get standards for organic produce. Better prices.
في شرق أفريقيا للحصول على معايير للمنتجات الزراعية العضوية. أسعار أفضل.
It ties in with small-scale farmers
للعلاقات مع صغار المزارعين
in terms of no pesticides, no fertilizers.
من حيث لا مبيدات، ولا أسمدة.
Again, opportunity to tackle markets to get that higher price.
مرة أخرى ، فرصة لمعالجة تلك الأسواق للحصول على سعر أعلى.
Uganda: the New Forest Company,
يوغندا: شركة الغابات الجديدة،
replanting and redeveloping their forests. Why is that important?
إعادة تطوير وإعادة زراعة الغابات. لماذا هو مهم؟
As the energy needs are met and electricity is needed [we will need]
كما نحتاج للطاقة أيضاً نحتاج للكهرباء [سنحتاج]
poles for rolling out electricity.
اقطاب لسحب الكهرباء للخارج.
But here is the sweetener in the deal.
ولكن هنا شئ لطيف في الصفقة.
They're going to be tapping into carbon credits.
سيقومون بإستغلال أرصدة الكربون.
Let's go back to Nigeria.
لنرجع لنيجيريا.
The banking sector has undergone tremendous transformation,
القطاع المصرفي لديه تحول هائل،
from over 80 banks to 25 banks. Strengthening of the system.
من أكثر من 80 إلى 25 بنكاً . يعززون النظام.
But what's going on there? Only 10 percent of the country is banked.
ولكن ما الذي يحصل هناك؟ فقط 10 في المائة من الدولة مرهونة.
The largest population in Africa is in Nigeria.
أكبر تعداد سكاني في أفريقيا هو في نيجيريا.
135 million-plus people. Think about that.
135 مليون شخص. فكروا في ذلك.
There are only 700 ATMs in the country. Opportunity.
هنالك فقط 700 جهاز صراف آلي في الدولة. فرصة.
The same for telecoms across the country.
نفس الشئ بالنسبة لشركات الإتصالات في الدولة.
Now let's look at the continent as a whole.
الآن دعونا نلقي نظرة للقارة ككل.
People look at the roads, for example, and they'd say,
الناس ينظرون للطرق، على سبيل المثال، سيقولون
"Angola: 90 percent of roads are untarred. Ah, problem!"
"أنجولا: 90 في المائة من طرقها لم تشيد. اه، مشكلة!"
It's more expensive to transport goods. Prices of goods go up,
هذا مكلف جداً للتنقل بشكل جيّد. أسعار الأشياء الجيدة ترتفع،
inflation is affected.
التضخم يتأثر.
Nigeria: 70 percent of roads are untarred. Zambia: 80 percent.
نيجيريا: 70 في المائة من الطرق غير مشيدة، زامبيا: 80 في المائة.
In general, more than 50 percent of roads are untarred.
وفي العموم، أكثر من 50 في المائة غير مشيدة.
This is an opportunity! Energy needs -- it's an opportunity.
هذه فرصة! إحتياجات الطاقة -- إنها فرصة.
So what are the signs that things are fundamentally changing?
إذاً ما هي الإشارات أن تلك الأشياء تتغير جوهرياً؟
Let's look at the stock markets in Africa.
لنلقي نظرة في أسهم الأسواق في أفريقيا.
If I had to ask you, "In 2005 what was the best performing stock market
إذا كان علي أن أسألكم، " في 2005 ما هو أفضل منفذ سوق أسهم
or stock exchange in the world?" Would Egypt come to mind?
أو تبادل الأسهم في العالم؟" هل مصر تتبادر إلى الذهن؟
In 2005, the Egyptian stock exchange returned over 145 percent.
في 2005، سوق الأسهم المصري -- تبادل الأسهم -- تجاوز الـ 45 في المائة.
What's going on in some of the other countries?
ما الذي يجري في بعض الدول الأخرى؟
Let's look at some 2006 numbers. Kenya: over 60 percent. Nigeria: over 40 percent.
لننظر إلى بعض أرقام 2006. كينيا: أكثر من 60 في المائة. نيجيريا: أكثر من 40 في المائة.
South Africa: in the 20 percents. High ones.
جنوب أفريقيا: في الـ 20 بالمائة. أعلى واحدة.
These are the trends that are taking place.
هذا هو الإتجاه الذي يأخذ مكانه.
But in any investment decision, the key question is,
ولكن في أي قرار إستثماري، السؤال الأساسي هو،
"What is my alternative investment?"
"ما هو بديلي للإستثمار ؟"
Because in Africa today, we are competing globally for capital.
ﻷن في أفريقيا اليوم، نحن ننافس عالمياً على رأس المال.
And global capital is agnostic -- it has no loyalties.
ورأس المال العالمي جبان -- ليس لديه ولاءات.
There's an overhang of capital in the U.S., and the key is yield pickup.
هناك فائض من رأس المال في الولايات المتحدة، والمفتاح هو تسريع الإلتقاط.
What Africa is providing is a diversification play,
ما تقدمه أفريقيا هو لعبة التنويع،
and also opportunities for yield pickup for the investor
والفرصة في تسريع الإنتاجية للمستثمرين
that's aware of what he or she is doing.
الواعين بما تفعله هي أو هو .
Now, when looking at Africa vis-a-vis other things,
الآن، عندما ننظر لأفريقيا وجه لوجه مع الأشياء الآخرى،
and countries in Africa vis-a-vis other things,
والدول في أفريقيا وجه لوجه مع الأشياء الأخرى،
comparisons become important.
المقارنات أصبحت مهمة.
10 years ago there, were very few countries
قبل 10 سنوات هناك، عندما كانت هناك القليل من الدول
that received sovereign ratings from
التي لاقت تصنيفات سيادية من
the Standard &amp; Poors, Moody's and Fitch's.
وكالة موديز ستاندرد أند بورز، من وكالة مووديز أن فيتشس..
Today, 16 African countries and growing
اليوم، لدى 16 دولة أفريقية ونامية
have sovereign country ratings. What does this mean?
تصنيف دولة سيادي، ماذا يعني هذا؟
Take Nigeria again: double B-minus --
خذوا نجيريا مجدداً : إثنين باء-ناقص (B-minus)--
in the league of Ukraine and Turkey. Immediately we have a comparison.
في رابطة مع أوكرانيا وتركيا. في الحال لدينا مقارنة.
The backbone of making investment decisions
الجزء الأهم في أخذ قرارات إستثمارية
for global holders of capital.
لأصحاب رؤوس الأموال العالمية.
Some other figures. South Africa: triple B-plus. Botswana: A-plus.
بعض الشخصيات الأخرى. جنوب أفريقيا: ثلاثة باء-زائد. بوتسوانا: الف-زائد.
Bakino Faso: B-minus. And so on.
بوركينا فاسو: باء-ناقص وهكذا.
In fact, one of the big agencies is setting up an office in Africa.
في الحقيقة، واحدة من أكبر الوكالات لديها مكتب في أفريقيا.
Why are they doing that? Because they expect investment to follow.
لماذا يفعلون ذلك؟ ﻷنهم يتوقعوا زيادة الإستثمار.
So one of the big bellwethers,
إذا واحدة من الشركات العملاقة،
and one of my final points I want to mention, is
وواحدة من نقاطي الأخيرة التي أريد أن أذكرها، هي
the interesting thing I read is that CNBC
الشئ المثير للإهتمام أنني قرأت: أن سي إن بي سي
has launched their first African channel. Why is CNBC doing this?
دشنوا قناتهم الأفريقية الأولى. لماذا سي إن بي سي تفعل ذلك؟
It's the 24-hour rolling African news channel.
انها قناة إخبارية تبث 24 ساعة عن أفريقيا.
They're doing it because they are expecting things to happen.
إنهم يفعلون ذلك ﻷنهم يتوقعون شيئاً ليحصل.
Me and you, the investments we are going to be making,
انا وأنتم، الإستثمارات التي سنصنعها،
the investments the world is going to be making --
الإستثمارات التي سيصنعها العالم --
that's the 24-hour news channel dedicated to Africa.
إن القناة الأخبارية التي تعمل 24 ساعة قد كُرست ﻷفريقيا.
So that's the change that's coming down the pipeline.
إذا التغيير يحصل في الإستقاء المباشر للأخبار.
So in conclusion, I want to turn back to that very slide
إذاً في الختام، أريد الرجوع لتلك اللوحة
that made such a deep impact on me all those years ago.
التي تركت فيّ أثراً عميقاً كل تلك السنيين الفائتة.
This time [I'll] give you the entire picture that I saw in 2002,
وفي هذا الوقت سوف أعطيكم الصورة التي رأيتها في 2002،
and ask you that when you think about what your role can be in Africa,
وأسألكم عن ماذا تعتقد سيكون دوركم في أفريقيا،
think about your journey in terms of bringing light to this continent.
فكروا في رحلتكم بشرط أن تجلبوا النور لتلك القارة
Because there are amazing opportunities available.
ﻷن هنالك فرص مذهلة متاحة.
And think about the concept of transformation
وفكروا في فهم التحول
in the back of your mind
في الجزء الخلفي من عقلكم ،
because things can be turned around rather quickly.
لأن الأمور يمكن ان تتبدل بسرعة.
In 1899, Joseph Conrad released "The Heart of Darkness,"
في 1899، أصدر جوزيف كورنارد "قلب الظلام،"
a tale of grim horror along the Congo River.
قصة رعب قاتمة على طول نهر الكونغو.
If one looks carefully, on the Congo River
لو نظر أحد بحذر، في نهر الكنغو
is one of those bright lights. And that's the very Congo river
هو أحد تلك الأضواء المشعة ، وهذا النهر الكونغولي تحديداً
generating light -- the old heart of darkness
يولد الضوء -- القلب القديم للظلام --
now generating light with hydro-electric power.
الآن يوليد الضوء بالطاقة الكهرومائية.
That is a transformation in power of ideas.
هذا هو التحول في طاقة الأفكار.
So the next step, over the next four days,
إذا الخطوة التالية، في الأربعة أيام التالية،
is us exploring more of these ideas.
هو ان نستكشف المزيد من هذه الأفكار.
And perchance, if you can always keep this picture in your mind,
وبالمصادفة، أذا أمكنك أن تحتفظ بهذه الصورة في ذهنك.
that when we convene maybe in the distant future, in 2020,
وأنه عندما نجتمع ربما في المستقبل المنظور ، في عام 2020 ،
that picture will look very different.
هذه الصورة ستبدو مختلفة جداً.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)